Guide to the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company Records, 1860-1999 AIS.1982.23
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad, 1860-1999; VII.
  - Financial, 1850-1994; 2.
    - Bertram Field and Edward L. Franucchi v. Henry G. Allyn, Jr.; Finance Auditors report; Wheeling Dollar Coal leases and valuation; stock buying reports; securities firms, 1979-1985 (Box 533)
    - ICC Hearing for B&O and P&LE featuring exhibits of employees, departmental duties, switching studies, tax and capital stock information, proposed usage payments, explanation of valuation figures, routes, statistics, land valuations, rehabilitation, costs, savings, 1963 (Oversize 569-570)
  - General Operations, 1883-1982; 3.
    This series represents records that do not fall exclusively under the other more specific categories. Boxes marked with this subseries name may contain a wide-ranging mix of records from different departments and have no clear distinction other than that they are examples of railroad operations, such as meeting minutes, personnel correspondence, and reports. All material formats may appear in this subseries.
    - Trainmen rosters (1980s), Bulletin Orders (1980s), Tax Assessments (1930), blueprints and work orders to Bethlehem Steel for rail cars and 250-ton steel wreck crane, 1930-1986 (Box 2)
    - Retirement roster; dinner information; disciplinary forms, passenger train service (1983), freight claim forms, 1980s (Box 7)
    - Youghiogheny Bridge Manteca files, Pittsburgh Train Shed files, insurance inquiry files and modification for compliance, 1940s (Box 9)
    - Air brake implementation, land lease, road crossing construction file, 1950-1980 (Box 10)
    - Land leases, power plant branch extension WV (blueprints) River-Lake belt conveyor study, 1940s (Box 17)
    - Photographs (Boiler Tube Company of America, Employees, Black Lung, Negatives Yard Photos, Scrapbook), telephone directory, blueprints (Montour Junction), Break Assembly Packet, Radio Procedure Cards, 1950-1980 (Box 21)
    - Correspondence, Dental Plan, Freight Shipment Claims, 1980s (Box 22)
    - Board of directors meeting minutes, Finance Committee Documents, 1980s (Box 23)
    - Trainmen seniority rosters, engineer investigations, accident reports, clerks roster, Conrail Qualifications, 1990s (Box 24)
    - Information on insurance company, parts/materials, fire losses, 1978-1988 (Box 26)
    - Passenger Service, Freight Operations, Security Files (order for new police vehicles - Ford Fairmonts, Dodge Aspens), 1970s (Box 27)
    - Facilities Information (McKee's Rocks; Homestead), 1960-1970 (Box 31)
    - Police dept. reports, leases and track agreements, rules and rates of pay agreement, 1980s (Box 33)
    - Microfilm records, safety rules, operating statistics and overhead expenses, Pocket Directory of Railroad Officials, change of employee status, disability files, 1980s (Box 35)
    - Documents Furnished PCTC Trustees, Re: Sale of P&LE (1977), Maintenance Chart, Equipment Lease Agreements, Lease Documents, Labor relations report, Bank Credit Agreement, 1970s (Box 74)
    - Report of Operations books (1921-25, 1934-35,1938-39, 1949), 1921-1949 (Box 84)
    - Annual Reports (1961-66), Sale of Land and Property, Lease of Land and Property, Phone and Wire Crossing files, Track Mileage and Grade Changes, 1960s (Box 86)
    - Business Orders (1988), Destruction of Records form (1965), blueprints for turntable, crane, etc., 1950-1980s (Box 92)
    - Community Relations Committee of the Pittsburgh Railroads Files - Countdown for America's Railroads, 1950-1980s (Box 147)
    - Reg. Files - Entire Road - Up to current files, American Railway Supervisors Association, 1960s (Box 155)
    - Various Letters (1960-74), 1120 Crossing Watchmen, Seniority Roster (1993), Brady Street Bridge (1970 - 1975), Store House at McKees Rocks (1986), Report on P&LE fueling facility at McKees Rocks, 1960s-1970s (Box 160)
    - Mgr. Business Planning & Analysis - Monongahela Through Power; Connellsville Coal Transfer; Smith's Ferry Branch; Brownsville Area Coal Transfer; Locomotive Sand; Utilization of Hoppers; Dickerson Run Coal Transfer; Southwest Steel Property; Lykes Resources - Emerald Mine - WSRR, 1970s (Box 176)
    - Correspondence on car movements, track changes, legal issues, 1983 Weed and Bush Control Program, and "5,000,000th Freight Car"/Gateway Yard Celebration (1966); rosters and seniority lists, notices and bulletins, 1924-1983 (Box 296b)
    - Correspondence of Chief Mechanical Officer regarding matters of the mechanical department such as railroad billing, employees, inspections, and announcements, 1982-1985 (Box 298a)
    - Frank Virant's school books, correspondence and records regarding labor discipline and investigation of civil suits and other legal matters, locomotive and other maintenance purchases, "dieselization" of College Station, contracts with North Star Coal Dock, weigh station sanctions (Box 329a)
    - Financial World Magazines 1930s-40s; Ads; American Railroad Car Institute Publication 1950s; correspondence, contracts regarding agreements between regional railroads; T&T publications-the American resistance movement; employee records; P&LE case against J.F. Kepler, 1909-1958 (Box 330)
    - NYC system instructions for operation of diesel-electric locomotives; files pertaining to ads on cars, station record of movements, wreck trucks; Newell accident report; card file of widows, pensioners, deceased, 1952-1988 (Box 333)
    - Statements and notices, financial correspondence and dockets, railroad publications, Electric Equipment and Wire Connections books, Short-Range Development Plan, and passenger questionnaires, statistics, 1932-1980 (Box 342a)
    - Records of 40-hour work week decision; correspondence concerning Pennsylvania Railroad bridge at Beaver Falls and New Brighton, bridge in Homestead, train accidents, and locomotive parts, 1898-1960 (Box 342b)
    - Youngstown Suburban Railroad Company minutes and record books, 1903-1925 (Box 350)
    - 3 large bound books of meeting minutes, 1918-1931 (Box 351)
    - General Notice Index; Falcon Club Auction log (1999); Employment Procedures (1950s); meeting minutes; Montour Railroad Annual Reports to Interstate Commerce Commission; Management Employee Handbook of P railroad company agreement books for P&LE, Lake Erie & Eastern Railroad, and United Transportation Union, 1934-1999 (Box 355)
    - Bound minutes, 1964-1987 (Box 359a-359b)
    - Numerous scrapbooks of the Upper Ohio River Valley Association which contain newspaper clippings, photos, resolutions, news releases, letters of opposition from local associations, 1939-1946 (Box 366)
    - Credit cards of vehicles assigned to equipment department; firemen's, engineer's, and clerk's agreements; Railroad Yardmasters of America and American Train Dispatchers agreements; Transportation-Communication Employees Union; general notices; 'pink sheets', 1956-1988 (Box 369)
    - Annual reports of the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie, Mahoning State Line, Monongahela Connecting, and Beaver & Ellwood railroads, 1901-1909 (Box 371)
    - Large bound minute books, 1956-1964 (Box 373)
    - Large bound minute books, 1932-1965 (Box 376)
    - Maintenance of Way agreements; P&LE news bureau releases; stockholder meetings; vendor brochures; published annual reports; Montour agreements; irregularities and disciplines; Youngstown Superintendent Association meeting notes and correspondence, 1960s-1970s (Box 379)
    - Locomotive study; cabin and caboose car information; freight car classifications; abandonments; equipment and building requirements; leases; rentals; sales; authorizations, 1965-1991 (Box 380)
    - Road switcher service; contracts with other railroads; locomotive requirements; Union Railroad Interchanges; caboose equipment list; Pittsburgh Landmark Foundation, 1953-1972 (Box 381)
    - Train movement reports (1973-77), radio and wireless communication (1987). Bow train, cabin, and caboose, 1973-1987 (Box 382)
    - Files include RRR Intersection, Y&ST, Brier Hill, revision; Committee of Youngstown; Joint Yard access; Mahoning Valley Region, 1924-1985 (Box 385b)
    - Correspondence and historical data of Waynesburg Southern Railroad Company, 1960s (Box 411)
    - Paperwork and correspondence between railroad and various labor unions, including strikes; disposal of hazardous waste and refuse; scrapped cars; office supply orders; news releases and articles concerning labor issues, accidents, and other company issues, 1969-1990 (Box 415b)
    - Flood Committee; sidetracks; maintenance and repair of diesel locomotives; study of Montour Railroad coal movements; joint facilities; flat car conversion design; centralized crew dispatching; cost analyses; Detroit-Edison train; hot slab trains; Aliquippa & Southern Railroad, 1897-1973 (Box 424)
    - Right of way; grade crossings; Anderson Road station; bridge repairs; highway construction; sidings; drainage at Blacks Run; land leases; agreement with other railroads, 1905-1965 (Box 425)
    - Signal failures and inspections; various improvements to Beaver Falls area; tracks at New Castle; property and automobile damages; land leases; company agreements; sidetracks; right of way, 1900-1960 (Box 426)
    - Change of highways; right of ways; property leases; pollution of streams in Allegheny County; various agreements and contracts; shop buildings at Davis Island Repair Yard, 1905-1948 (Box 430)
    - Sidetrack agreements; regulations of Destruction of Records of Steam Railroads and McKees Rocks storage; sidings; pymatuning and draining of swamp; YMCA facilities; widening of East Carson Street; statistics of Youngstown, Oh. YMCA, 1901-1958 (Box 431)
    - Correspondence concerning highway between Monaca and Aliquippa; right of way at Monaca; scrap plant shipments; Beaver River bridge repairs; Port Perry Yard extensions; Ambridge highway bridge, 1900-1956 (Box 432)
    - Recapitulation of engine hours in East Youngstown District; yardmaster dismissals; statements of trackage, cars handled through various yards, car, engine, and caboose mileage; weight and motion scales; Fourth Avenue Project in McKeesport; yardmaster promotions; matters of Lake Erie & Ohio River Canal; memberships in organizations, 1966-1992 (Box 433)
    - Personal Injuries; company vehicles; repairs to and information on freight equipment, information regarding freight equipment, 1969-1987 (Box 434)
    - Lazarri land purchase; sign placement and construction at numerous stations; construction of utility wires along rail line; construction and maintenance of crossings; advanced rate case; employee sight and hearing exams; P&LE YMCA building construction and maintenance; north pole ice company land, death of trespasser and improvements due to, 1912-1959 (Box 437)
    - Electrical requisitions of Mechanical Department; Arbitration Committee minutes and decisions; purchase orders; freight car inventories; Association of American Railroad Manual of Standards and Practices; AAR special reports; vehicles file; card index of railroads; gas receipts, 1980-1990 (Box 438)
    - Bulletin Order Book, 1989 (Box 440b)
    - Contracts on Youngstown area for joint use of rails, cars, fuel; liability contracts, correspondence; Mon Valley Newspaper, 1923-1992 (Box 441)
    - PL&W Railroad accounting, Association of American Railroads bulletins; audits; social security; retirement; correspondence with oil companies; wage increases; state highway department, 1925-1945 (Box 442a)
    - War Production Board forms and correspondence, Office of Defense Transportation notices and correspondence, American Railway Express bulletins, invoices, annual returns, 1925-1945 (Box 442b)
    - Check invoices; company work vehicles; gas and steel corporations, 1980-1990 (Box 443)
    - Instructions for Materials Requisitions; joint car records; reports to Interstate Commerce Commission; instructions for interchanges; Hours of Service Law; Track-Train Dynamics; freight car safety standards; car utilization program; patents; occupation taxes, 1929-1990 (Box 445)
    - Cars assigned to special service; weekly man counts; Morning Situation Reports; Daily Yard Crew Reports; General Superintendent 'Pink Sheets', 1981-1992 (Box 447a)
    - General Superintendent 'Pink Sheets', 1982-1987 (Box 447b)
    - Visual and hearing exams; Metals Recycling; car cleaning services; inspections; Intra-Industry Claims Agreement; Track Torpedoes specs and use; Fire and Trainmen Exams; expense accounts; Mechanized Information System; medical exams, 1926-1989 (Box 450)
    - Various publications on industry research; publications from conference proceedings and workshops; P&LE employee handbook; Carnegie Steel publication on "rails and angle bars;" worker safety pamphlets, 1920-1982 (Box 451)
    - Records, agreements, and plans regarding the restructuring of railroad, 1985 (Box 455)
    - Physical condition of property reports; air brake testing devices; shop inspections; vehicle bills; Machine & Tool Program; permits to visit yards and shops, 1960-1981 (Box 458)
    - Accident reports, mostly derailments, 1967-1978 (Box 459)
    - Finance; account book (1980s); Chief Engineers' office files on The Nation Supply Company, formerly Union Tool Company, Taulor Forge and Pipe Works, Inc. (1910-46), photographs; PC&Y Railroad file on Scott Twp, 1910-1980s (Box 464)
    - Reports and correspondence of CSX; P&LE phone directory; employee General Notices (1980s); union information; Montour and PC&Y, car service rules; Connellsville machinery, passenger cars, environmental concerns and correspondence; radios (1981-91); contract services provided by P agreements with CIO; TWU correspondence and reports; Employee Assistance Program booklet; claims against Montour Railroad, 1981-1992 (Box 467)
    - Equipment and service orders and requests; bills; estimates; blanket authorizations and authority for expenditure; accident reports; powerhouse reports, 1974-1986 (Box 472)
    - Wheeling-Pittsburgh Steel Corporation hot slab movement; postage meter machine bills; supplementary pension-funded contributory retirement plan; allowances account for sick or dead employees; hot metal movements (McKeesport, Neville Island, etc), 1936-1985 (Box 479)
    - Program of Cooperative Research prospectus; Baltimore & Ohio Railroad Company application and finance dockets, statistics, weather records, track maintenance, proposals, 1962-1963 (Box 482)
    - Regulations of Public Utility Commission; vending machine services contracts; organization of officials charts; contracts and agreements with Consolidated Rail Corp. and P&LE-Ashtabula Harbor Agreement; ICC locomotive inspections; relations with Dept. of US Government Presidential Advisory Committee on Railroads, 1928-1989 (Box 483)
    - Railroad toilet facilities reports; various train reports; time tables and schedules; operation of B&O trains over P&LE railroads; contracts and agreements with B&O; contracts and agreements with various companies and railroads; P&LE and PC&Y joint inspection and equipment maintenance; line service to Erie, PL&E, B&O, Cleveland, Pittsburgh, and Baltimore, 1928-1982 (Box 485)
    - Board of Directors meeting minutes; Penn Central Transportation Company reorganization proceedings; Mary Crowell et. al vs. P&LE Railroad Company litigation records (court reports and bills, etc.), 1969-1974 (Box 486)
    - Annual reports to Ohio Department of Taxation (1991); Interstate Commerce Commission applications for construction approval; Who's Who In America lawyer directory; submissions for RR execs; Oliver Iron and Steel Corp purchase of riverfront property legal documents; inspection trips; file of Alfred E. Perlman speech to Newcomen Society; National Association Railroad and Utility Commission; grade crossings; land purchases; Conrail agreements; increased freight rates and charges (1957); LE&E files, 1970-1991 (Box 493)
    - Personal injury and relative insurance paperwork, Association of American Railroads efficiency research program, AAR manual of standards and records practices, vendor offers, 1972-1984 (Box 499)
    - Shop maintenance standards (1986); multi-railroad agreements on car men, their helpers, and apprentices (1963); agreement between PA railroads and American Railway Supervisors Association (1957); master agreement for restructuring of obligations of P&LE (1985); various other multi-railroad agreements; Montour Railroad railway operating revenues (1927-1941), 1927-1986 (Box 517)
    - R.F.A. and A.F.E. Instructions and Budget Procedures; information and correspondence concerning budgeting for hot water boiling, conditioning systems, furnace, water softener, etc., 1959-1972 (Box 518a)
    - Information and correspondence concerning budgeting for hot water boiling, conditioning systems, furnace, water softener, etc; Consol Coal railroad spur; equipment sales exchange, 1965-1981 (Box 518b)
    - P&LE Annual Reports (1963-78); GM Master Parts Catalogs; Pocket List of Railroad Officials (1989), 1963-1989 (Box 521b)
    - Correspondence from Chief Engineer's Office: Equipment and purchase orders, employee age limits; publication information; Youngstown & Southern Railroad Transfer Contract; physical requirements; matters of signals, transportation, and storage; test equipment; microfiches of interchange, 1932-1989 (Box 524)
    - Property exchanges and agreements; Electrical Workers Organization correspondence; side track agreements; land leases; track crossings, 1899-1960 (Box 526)
    - New York Central Improvement Program; employee cards; presentation to creditors; union agreements; coal deliveries; land contracts, 1923-1986 (Box 527)
    - Annual reports, financial statements for PLECO Inc. and subsidiaries; valuation book; locomotive replacement report; field notes; 'Pink Sheet' book, 1880s-1990 (Box 529a)
    - Report and recommendations of United Transportation Union study committee; various publications including testimony transcripts; report on trends of railroad construction costs; shipment conditions; research reports of Federal Railroad Administration; Annual Reports of National Mediation Board; Railway Accounting Rules; ICC Amendments, Rules, and Dockets; Constitution and annual report of American Short Line Railroad Association; Public Utility Law, etc., 1923-1992 (Box 532)
    - PC&Y annual reports of maintenance of way (1925-30); O.S. reports (1898-1943); Allegheny County record book; book of right of way deeds; train orders; flood planning information; Penn Central procedures for Capital Projects (1968); testimony of PLW President and Director, 1898-1968 (Box 534)
    - Various departmental agreements; employee pensions retirement, and hiring; interchange agreements and car reports, 1982-1988 (Box 543a)
    - Bulletins and general notices concerning cargo, cars, shipment instructions, transferred loads; correspondence regarding claims and "safety first", 1979 (Box 544a)
    - Bulletins and general notices regarding P&LE, Conrail, YS&T; bills; correspondence with numerous steel yards, 1978-1979 (Box 544b)
    - Pilot write-ups; Conrail and Chessie car reclaims; qualifications, 1985-1989 (Box 545a)
    - Trackage and interchange agreements; joint-use agreement between P&LE and New York Central Railroad; agreements with Youngstown rail yard; 1977 investigation into the incorrect handling of car, 1928-1989 (Box 545b)
    - Movement of cars; car inventory; coal; janitorial; office supplies; time claims; sidetrack agreements; cargo, careful handling, 1973 (Box 546b)
    - Time claims, "safety first" correspondence; personal injury; car accidents; general notices and bulletins; bills; cost operations, 1973-1979 (Box 547a)
    - Youngstown & Southern general notices and switch agreements; Republic Steel general notices and switch agreements; USS general notices; car reclaims; Penn Central correspondence, 1970-1975 (Box 547b)
    - Freight car ownership logs; maintenance of equipment and freight cars; sale orders; leased car file; terminal building development; re-stenciled cars; car retirement sheets. Montour Railroad and Youngstown & Southern Railroad monthly reports of revenue freight cars, 1970-1990 (Box 552a)
    - Schedules of rates and surcharges for billing railroads for use of facilities, services, and equipment; office manual of Association of American Railroads Interchange Rules, 1980s (Box 558)
    - Various documents including Ohio Legislature; booklet on wrought iron (1960); equipment department file index; cassette tapes on Air Brakes; packet of color photographs from Aliquippa Southern Railroad (1981); aperture card; folder containing selection of blank P&LE and Montour Railroad forms and cards; photograph of railroad personnel; copy of P&LE patent, 1913-1980 (Box 564)
    - Index cards of companies, transactions, and contracts, 1900-1960 (Box 567)
    - Daily reports of materials received, used, shipped, and released by P&LE lines, 1963 (Oversize 577)
    - Monthly Report of Operations and Statistics, 1920-1978 (Box 614-619)
  - Labor, 1850-1994; 4.
    The Labor series covers most employee matters, including but not limited to, applications, interviews, pay rates, injuries, illness, vacation, employee information, grievances, and any manner of documentation that relates to the life of a P&LE Railroad employee.
    - Out of service employee records A-I, 1880-1950 (Box 11)
    - Out of service employee records J-R, 1880-1950 (Box 12)
    - Out of service employee records S-Z, 1880-1950 (Box 13)
    - Military Leave employee records A-Z, In service electricians A-Z, 1880-1950 (Box 14)
    - Powerhouse furloughed A-Z, 1880-1950 (Box 15)
    - Requirements for employees, College Recruitment Program, rules governing employees, age limits, Pension Plan, safety meetings, safety eye glasses, 1970s (Box 18)
    - Trainmen seniority rosters, engineer investigations, accident reports, clerks roster, Conrail Qualifications, 1990s (Box 24)
    - Employee Accounts and Wages, Method of Paying Employees, General Employee Operations Files, 1970s (Box 29)
    - Employees not returning from military leave, job ads, rates of pay (1965), CAB report, Seniority District, Forecasts and expenditure reports (1985), 1962-1985 (Box 34)
    - Microfilm records, Safety Rules, Operating Statistics and Overhead Expenses, Pocket Directory of Railroad Officials, Change of Employee Status- Disability Files, 1980s (Box 35)
    - Employee Record Cards, 1880s-1950 (Box 52-56)
    - Employee Records, 1800s-1950 (Box 53)
    - Personal injury files from Allegheny County Court of Common Pleas, 1970s (Box 72)
    - Trainmen's and clerks rosters, time sheets and books, P&LE Phone Directory, position changes, time disagreement files, 1992 Morning Situation Report, 1960-1970 (Box 73)
    - Documents Furnished PCTC Trustees, Re: Sale of P&LE (1977), Maintenance Chart, Equipment Lease Agreements, Lease Documents, Labor relations report, Bank Credit Agreement, 1970s (Box 74)
    - Personal injury Files, Mechanical Department, 1949-1950 (Box 87-88)
    - Union Shop Agreement files, 1960 (Box 90)
    - General Files - Discipline of Employee's - Mechanical Department, 1960s-1970s (Box 91)
    - Employment of Women, Penn Central Merger, Clerks and Foremen Agreements, 1970-1980 (Box 103)
    - Employee Records (leave of absence documents, furloughed, etc), Union Rosters, Car Dept Roster (1988), 1950-1990 (Box 104)
    - Mechanical Dept. - Transport Workers of America Cases ( MY -1 to My - 61 - A and G - 2 to G - 75), 1960s (Box 146)
    - Labor Relations and Personnel Department - Agreements (Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, United Transportation Union, Train Dispatchers Agreement, Wage Stabilization Agreement Protected Clerks), monthly displacement allowance, Pink Sheet Copies, 1970s-1980s (Box 149)